<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Anglorum singultus: or, The sobbs of England, poured out. To be presented to His Excellency Generall George Monke.</title>
            <author>Peirce, Edmund, Sir, d. 1667.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 23 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90358</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P1059</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E774_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203311</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863297</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863297</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115489</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90358)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115489)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 118:E774[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Anglorum singultus: or, The sobbs of England, poured out. To be presented to His Excellency Generall George Monke.</title>
                  <author>Peirce, Edmund, Sir, d. 1667.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>11, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for D.L.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Sir Edmund Peirce by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Feb: 2. 1659".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Albemarle, George Monck, --  Duke of, 1608-1670.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115489:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ANGLORUM SINGULTUS: OR, THE SOBBS OF ENGLAND, Poured out.</p>
            <p>To be preſented to His Excellency GENERALL <hi>GEORGE MONKE.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>D. L.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:115489:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:115489:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Anglorum Singultus:</hi> OR, The Sobs of <hi>England</hi> poured out: To be preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his Excellency, General <hi>George Monke.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He hopes which was generally raiſed in the ſpirits of all men, who have any true ſence of the blee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding and gaſping condition of the three once famous and flouriſhing Nations, of <hi>England, Scotland,</hi> and <hi>Ireland,</hi> have received ſome Check, by what is publiſhed, of the minde and intentions of your Excellency, in relation to the publique af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs; yet can we not conceive them utterly blaſted, whilſt we remember, you are a Chriſtian, an Engliſh-man, and a Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and one whoſe Prudence and Pollicy in the conduct of Affairs both Civil and Military, hath appeared ſignal and emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent amidſt the many ſtormy violences, which, of late years, have ſo much, and ſo often threatned our utter ruine and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, both in Church, State, and Common-wealth: Oh let not the Syrens of blood and miſchief further charm your ears, and delude your apprehenſion, by many ſpecious pretences, and beguiling ſuggeſtions, come they cloathed in what ſhape or co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour ſoever: But keep thoſe <hi>Scintillas divinae facis,</hi> thoſe divine faculties of your ſoul, your Underſtanding, Reaſon, and Will, free and untainted from all the inchanting allurements of pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate intereſt and Faction; and with the generous ſoul of a free-born Native of this Land, look about you, and with true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian compaſſion behold the new Chains and Fetters, which the black Operators of miſchief are now afreſh hammering, upon your Anvil, and with your Tools. It is now compleat eleven years, ſince that fatal and horrid act, that <hi>Crimen fulmine dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num,</hi> executed by the wicked Inſtruments of him, from whoſe dark conclave of Fiends it had its product? You that hitherto have ſtood free from the gnawing guilt of ſo direfull, grand, and piacular a crime, have ſo much pity upon your own ſoul and
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115489:3"/>honour, as not to ſully either, with ſo much contamination, as to enter Councels, much leſſe Intereſts, with that bloody crew, of the moſt diabolical humanities, which cloathed with fleſh and blood, ever entred the ſtage hf this world in any age or place whatſoever, ſince <hi>Adam</hi> digg'd for his firſt tranſgreſſion in <hi>Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe.</hi> To ſay nothing of what preceded, but to take a ſhort view and glance towards the diſmal waſting, and deſtructive contin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gencies, which in thoſe ſad eleven years have befaln us, <hi>viz.</hi> ſince <hi>Decemb.</hi> 5. 1648. from which time the firſt grand Contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of all our deplorable miſeries, began with bare face, to ſhew their horrid ſhape; what have we had ſince that time, but a continued concatination of ſucceſſive miſchiefs, one ruſhing up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the neck of another, and all under the guilded ſhew of a free Commonwealth; when, of all the true real and eſſential parts thereof, we have enjoyed not ſo much as the leaſt glimpſe or <hi>iota?</hi> Was there ever upon earth any ſtate and ſociety of men, who in ſo few years have endured ſuch, and ſo many bitter pangs and throws of viciſſitudinous thraldom, as we ſince that tiem have done? What heaving and ſhooving have we often tremblingly beheld for the Empire and Dominion over us, and in whoſe hand that iron Rod ſhould be that we poor Vaſſals were (however) to be ſcourged with? and when ambition had climbed and even reached the very pinacle of its aſpirings, what ſudden and ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendious revolutions have afreſh aſſaulted and amazed us? What a deluge of innocent bloud (now crying under the Altar) hath been waded through, to graſp, and aſſert the grandeur for ſome perſons; and what millions of treaſures (all robbed and extorted from us) have been ſquandred by every uppermoſt Power to ſupport its own uſurpation and greatneſſe? and we poor hackney'd, ſpurr'd and galled people, held under a ſevere and imperious charge and command to believe, that all this while, we were a free Common-wealth, and had gained that liberty which we were ſeduced ſo long, and vigorouſly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend for; although the chains of this our cruel bondage lay ſo hard and heavy upon us, as that they even fretted and eat into our very bowels and vitals: Are we not from hence become the ſcorn of our neighbour Nations, and without Gods infinite mercy very likely to become ſome of their prey? Was ever poor Church, State, and Commonwealth (twenty years ſince the wonder and envy of the whole Chriſtian world) reduced by a
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115489:3"/>few of its own members, moſt of them of meaneſt birth, and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all of inconſiderable quality, to ſuch a condition as we are? even the baſeſt, and moſt vile of all ſlavery and ſervitude, that ever was known or heard of among the ſons of Chriſtian men? And any thing which but looks like freedom, ſo utterly baniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed from us, that it is almoſt become treaſon, to name or men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion the word (FREE;) no, not in relation to that authority which cals it ſelf ſupream; we muſt not dare ſpeak, much leſſe declare our deſires to have a Free Parliament; if ſo, whips of Steel are providing for us, to tear off that little fleſh which yet remains upon our ſo much bloodied and bruiſed bones: What the intereſt and aims of private and particular Factions and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons are, it is, by many ſad experiences, become moſt appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently evident, and no longer to be obſcured, under any ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and gloſſy terms whatſoever, invented only to dazle and amuſe the vulgar and common notions, which have been ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten cheated and deluded by them. The true proper and gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral intereſt of the People and Nation undoubtedly is, The ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and ſecuring of the ancient and known fundamental Laws of the Land, upon which depends the property and true liberty of every individual member, the reviving and reſtoring of our languiſhing and dead Trade, both at home and abroad, which together with our traffique manufactures is by our ruinous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders frighted from us to our neighbour Nations: To ſettle and eſtabliſh Religion, that great and ſure bond which faſtens our ſecurities all other wayes: The procuring (after ſuch fatal ſtorms of feud and animoſity amongſt us, and ſomething elſe of a higher nature) a ſure, firm and generall indempnity for all paſt actions whatſoever: To have the Government in ſuch hands as may ſecurely ſettle our forreign allyances, whoſe particular intereſt is involved in the publique, and buton'd by a Title and juſt poſſeſſion, which needs not a conſuming exorbitant, and all terrifying force, and power to defend and ſupport it. Theſe at preſent are the chiefe points of the Nations true intereſt: And where can theſe things be treated, debated, and concluded of, with any good fruit or effect, or the leaſt hope thereof, bu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in a full and free Parliament, and the whole Nations convention? What is it, that makes this word (Free) ſo terrible, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable to ſome perſons? is force ſo pleaſing and delightſome to them: why then did they ſo lately and loudly call and cry out
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115489:4"/>for help and aſſiſtance againſt it? And yet no ſooner by the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions joynt concurrence delivered from it, but immediatly they fall to put the ſame in practice upon ſuch their deliverers, and continue it upon them with far more dread and terror than it was in any ſort ever exerciſed upon themſelves, in their utmoſt extremity. Muſt a ſmall cantel of the ſubſtitutes only enjoy freedom, and the reſidue ſubſtituted, being almoſt ten times their number, together with the whole body of the Nation ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituring, be kept under a force? Is freedom only the portion of ſome few the meaneſt of the people, and force to be entailed upon all the reſt, to all eternity: Or be we in a dream all this while, or ſo ſtupidly ignorant, as not to underſtand, what is force, or what is freedom? Or doth the ſeaſon or circumſtance of time, alter the nature of one and the ſelf ſame act <hi>in omni modo?</hi> Is that force in 1653. and the ſame thing not force in 1648. and 1649? Do thoſe men who thus, as it were ſport them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves with our miſery, and their own uſurped Empire, think that the eyes of God, Angels and men, are all ſhut, and that none beholds this their grand tyrannical and deluding im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſture?</p>
            <p>There hath been, and may be ſo much truly ſaid, in this and many other particulars, that it ſeems no leſſe than a kind of wonder, that there ſhould be ſuch a ſort of Natives of this Land, endued with reaſon, and ſuch refined reaſon, as pretends to the ſteerage and government of three ancient, potent and flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing Monarchies, and yet ſhould openly dare to breath the comon air thereof, whilſt with ſevereſt rigor, they impoſe ſuch the moſt indign of all prevarications upon it, and ſeem to have ſuch confidence in their acts of tyranny and force, that although (if they go on thus) their infamous ruine is ſo apparent to all ſober by-ſtanders, and cannot ſurely be otherwiſe to themſelves likewiſe in their own ſecret thoughts; yet are they ſo hurried on by that Monſter Ambition (<hi>Heroſtratus</hi>-like) to put all into a flame rather than ſuffer their hot and high aſpirings in the leaſt to chil or take cold, till themſelves and their deſignes drop into aſhes and rubbiſh.</p>
            <p>It is you (Great Sir) who have been long lookt upon as the Grand Moderator between theſe few unparalleld men, and this whole Nation, with all its Dominions, all the Nobility, Body of the Gentry, and Commons of the ſame; every County, City
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:115489:4"/>and Burrough, and indeed every degree and ſociety of men throughout the ſame; ſuch eſpecially as have at any time been engaged in the late war upon the Parliament account (and not now in arms) hereby joyntly as one man Addreſſing themſelves to you, as the onely <hi>Eſculapius</hi> to apply a ſeaſonable remedy to this malady of Force, which is the epedemical and contagious diſeaſe, that hath ſo long, and now more then ever corrodes and plagues us, and ſo much diſtorts our eaſe, ſettlement and quiet: You have brought with you ſtore of medicaments of all ſorts, potent Antidotes againſt the malignity of forcible power, and ſubtle impoſture, nor want you skill and courage ſeaſonably to apply them; we regard not the lying Trump of Fame, which publiſhes various ſtories of your being already en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged againſt us, and come rather to ſhackle us faſter, then looſe us from our long endured chains, to pull off our very skins which are already ſo cloſe clipt by our ſhearers, rather then to afford us any eaſe or reluxation from our long endured miſery. Much leſs do we credit that vain and empty whiſper of your pretence of title to the Crown, as of the blood of a <hi>Plantagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net.</hi> Theſe we look upon as inventions, raiſed by ſuch as to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain us ſtill in ſlavery, would have us think, that the ſcorching oyle in the frying pan, is more tollerable than the glowing heat of the fire; we are very well acquainted with ſubtleties of this kind, and are moſt confidently perſwaded, that your prudence and experience is ſuch, that (would Religion and conſcience permit in you ſuch an attempt yet) the late ruinous downfal and expoſition to general contempt, infamy and ſcorn of the Perſon and Family, and almoſt whole Allyance of ſuch a da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Uſurper, is ſo freſh in memory, and ſo viſibly and appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rently acted by Divine Providence in the very ſummity and height of their glory; that the very thought of ſuch an aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piring, will be moſt execrable and abhorrent to you: The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of this Nation and its Dominions, having in that par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular much reſemblance to the Arke of God, which till it came again into its right appointed place, was but a burden and plague almoſt to the utter deſtruction of whoſoever durſt ſet upon the retaining of it; witneſs our many late revolutions, and in them the downfal and ſuddain precipice of almoſt all that have in any ſort taken upon them its ſteerage and manage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: To ſay nothing of the ſignal judgements, which have
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115489:5"/>not been infrequently viſible amongſt us, upon ſuch as have been eminently active in its firſt unhinging.</p>
            <p>There are many particulars more to be hinted, much too long for this Paper, yet very neceſſary for your advertiſement; ſo that if freedome of argument in writing, or otherwiſe, were by your favour and indulgence to be uſed, without the danger u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſually in theſe times attending it: That which is ſaid to be your Letter into the <hi>Weſt,</hi> would ſoon cleerly appear to you, to be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Paradoxal,</hi> and as <hi>Hetrogenean</hi> to true policy, as deteſtable to all piety.</p>
            <p>All new by-paths, though ſomewhat trodden before experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence ſhews us, will certainly lead to no other place but preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pice and ruine; for whatſoever is contrariant to the ancient ſetled foundation, upon which (if duely and without prejudice conſidered) we are ſo evenly and ſo excellently bottomed, though to ſuch as look with falſe and bribed ſpectacles; the ſame may ſeem plauſible, plain and eaſie of digeſtion; yet it is almoſt impoſſible, but that there muſt needs be thence a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duction of the ſame evils, which have been acted amongſt us un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der ſeveral ſhapes and forms, ever ſince the year, 1648. And which will as certainly and undoubtedly return and ruſh in again upon us, and that the ſame cauſes cannot in nature but produce the ſame effects, and this without any difficulty is cleerly and infallibly to be demonſtrated to each rational and capable ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion; if pens were permitted that freedome to unde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, as they are countenanced, nay hyred to becloud, corrupt, and inſnare men, that ſo their chains and bonds of ſlavery and ſervitude may appear ſomewhat neceſſarily to be continued up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them; and whatſoever tyranny and vaſſaledge they under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>go and feel, they muſt yet believe (becauſe they are ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded) that it is liberty and freedome which they enjoy, and that they are Members of a Free-State and Common-wealth.</p>
            <p>The way you are deſired to walk in, is not at all obſcure; but as it is plain and eaſie; ſo is it moſt open, cleer and mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt to all prudent and unbyaſſed men, free from ſelf intereſt and partiality; ſuch as we doubt not but to find your Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency; eſpecially (<hi>dum res ſit integra,</hi> with you, and before you drink deeper of the cup of inchantment prepared for you) if you will pleaſe but ſeriouſlly to caſt your thoughts upon, believe truths, and duely conſider the preparations and reſolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115489:5"/>abroad: And with the tender bowels of a true <hi>Engliſh</hi> Gentleman to ponder the moſt earneſt and intenſe deſires (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt to rude clamors) at home, of all ſorts from the higheſt to the loweſt, and in all parts and places of the Nation; and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve your ſelf fortified againſt the allurements, and not be taken with the ſeeming bounties, but really empty husks, of thoſe who (though at preſent you are the darling of their courtſhip) yet you may be ſure, intend no further to honour you, then as it is uſeful for themſelves, nor make uſe of you longer, than (after their own turn is ſerved) they have an op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity and power to cruſh and deſtroy you; which as is cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dibly reported, an eminent one amongſt them, not long ſince affirmed in effect to his Friend.</p>
            <p>Providence hath brought it ſo to paſs, that you have now the ſcale of your future fortunes in your own hands; be wary how you poize them, and look circumſpectly to the weight in each ſcale; and take heed you make not the droſs weigh down the gold. It is now undoubtedly in your power to ſettle firmly and laſtingly the peace and quiet of this ſo long miſerably torn and waſted Nation, and that in all probability, without the leaſt drop of blood: A piece of Honour and Chriſtianity, which hitherto hath not been vouchſafed ſo cleerly to any perſon or power whatſoever, ſince our fatal and unhappy ſtruglings: Looſe not this your happy and glorious opportunity, (as divers others have done theirs, and periſhed) leaſt any glimpſe thereof never dawn more to you: The cure is ſo eaſie (done with a word or two, <hi>A Free Parliament</hi>) and ſo natural for the malady and diſtemper; that ſurely it would be the greateſt of all ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannical cruelties, to ſuffer a longer perſeverance in denying ſo certain a remedy for ſuch a ſore and deſperate evil; you have potent Arguments Sir, and ſuch only they are, which the grand Oppoſers and our tormentors have uſed themſelves to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinced by: Oh look upon, and more than ſeriouſly conſider the rufull and deplorable condition which your poor Mother Nation, without this your interceſſion, will moſt unavoidably and deſperately be involved in. Think upon her, and her Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches former and ineffable ſufferings; and let her not be denied this one boon ſo neceſſary to preſerve her from final and utter deſtruction; ſhe (as it were upon her bare and bended knees) begs this from you, her own Son; and that it may be ſpeedy and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115489:6"/>effectual, not hampred and ſhackled with (we know not what) abſurd and empty previous Votes, made by a handfull of incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiderate and corrupt intereſſed men, to the infamy, ſtain, and diſhonour of thoſe grave, high and honorable Aſſemblies, but free and abſolute, without any dread, force, reſtriction, or aw upon it, which really and indeed deſtroyes its very eſſence, and renders it a meer ſlaviſh, captived Conventicle, and no true En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Parliament: By which, and no other way or remedy under Heaven, ſhe can hope to obtain any effectual and ſucceſsful cure; agd which by your means procured for her, ſhall immortalize your fame and renown, not only through theſe Nations, but through the whole Chriſtian world, and merit Trophees of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be erected to you; and your Name and Poſterity by all ſorts and degrees of men, be juſtly magnified and exalted, ſo that no length of time ſhall defeat its juſt merit, but the ſame remain upon record to all ſucceeding generations.</p>
            <p>But yet after all theſe hopes, and expectations of your gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous integrity, if you ſhall, by what allurements whatſoever, be warped and wreſted from this undoubted true intereſt of your own and your Mother Countrey, and ſhall comply with that rotten Rump, and Bob-tail of a Parliament, the moſt baſe and unworthy for all ſiniſter and corrupt intereſt and faction that ever entred the wals of any of our Engliſh high Aſſemblies; in ſo much that never any crew of men, ſince this Iſland was firſt peopled, how vile and bad ſoever, incurred more than they, ſuch <hi>odium,</hi> ſcorn and contempt from all ſorts and degrees of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, from the higheſt to the loweſt, throughout the whole Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which may be eaſily heard and ſeen, not only in the open ſtreets chanted out in Rithmes and Sonnets, but upon the wals of almoſt every Ale-houſe and Tipling-hutch; yet if ſuch be the power of their Rhetorique to perſwade, and your faculty to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve and comply, then look to your ſtation, and the Reed you chooſe to lean on, for you will aſſuredly finde your ground very ſlippery; and your ſeeming ſupport, though weak in it ſelf, yet piercing your hands; and although perhaps you may ſeem to flouriſh a while, and ſwallow down great hopes, yet be aſſured they will never come to good digeſtion, but muſt up again: The incenſed Nation, though dejected for a time, will again rouze themſelves, and never forget the deluſion, cheat, and indeed no other than an abſolute <hi>Tre-pan</hi> put upon them, by which ſo
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115489:6"/>many of them have incurred ſome hazard and danger, and all from the good hopes they had of your prndence and integrity, and your loyalty and good intentions to the true National inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt, which you ſeemed ſo much to profeſſe, and plainly aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſame in your Anſwer to the City of <hi>London</hi>'s Letter, tel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling them, that you concurred with them in their Declaration, which in expreſſe words was for the obtaining of a Free Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; nor can your <hi>Mermidons</hi> help you at the long run nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; but you and your poſterity will finde your name and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory noyſomly ſtink in the noſtrils of all good and ſober men; and your <hi>Exit</hi> (at leaſt of honour) in all probability become more ſpeedy than tis poſſible you now deny or imagine, and that in the moſt abject and contemptible kinde of all others your fellow-deſtroyers and Ruiners of three famous and potent Kingdoms; nor will that be the worſt neither. There is an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count likewiſe to be given (a very deadful one) at that impartial bar of the great and general Tribunal, where no martial force, pomp or pollicy, will at all be prevalent; and where perhaps this very paper, (if ſlighted by you) may add ſomething to your aſtoniſhment and confuſion.</p>
            <p>But we yet hope better things from your Excellency, and ſuch as ſhall be worthy your ſelf, as you are a Chriſtian, a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, and an Engliſhman, and one ſo eminent, whoſe lot it is, to be furniſhed with that power in ſuch a conjuncture of time as this, that if you pleaſe but to pronounce the deſired word only, all our miſeries end, and our chains immediately fall off, which otherwiſe may be ſomewhat laſting, upon us; yet ſuch is our hope and confidence in the great Diſpoſer of all things, that we dare in faith and ſincerity uſe the words of <hi>Mordecai</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Gods people, recorded by the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Eſther</hi> 4.14. <hi>Deliverance ſhall ariſe from another place, and thou and thy Fathers Houſe ſhall be deſtroyed, and who knows whether thou art come to this honour for ſuch a time as this? &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But we retire, ſtand ſtill, and expect, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
